Finding aid to the Joan Banks Dunlop papers SSC.MS.00707
Sophia Smith Collection
Joan Banks Dunlop papers
1916-2012
Sophia Smith Collection
Dunlop, Joan Banks
SSC.MS.00707
10.125 linear feet (13 containers)
The Joan Banks Dunlop collection documents the life and work of Dunlop, an activist and leader in women's rights and reproductive health. Especially well documented is the work Dunlop did with IWHC and A Women's Lens on Global Issues.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use with following restrictions on access: Materials related to Joan Dunlop's divorce from Peter Dunlop and from Ed Deagle to be closed for 15 years (Jan. 1, 2028). Materials related to Adrienne Germain's departure from IWHC and Francoise Girard's appointment as President of IWHC to be closes for 20 years (Jan. 1, 2033).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Joann R. West on 2012-12-10.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged so that related materials are located in the same folders. Professional record from various organizations that Dunlop worked in are at the begining of the collection, in roughly chronological order, and other professional and personal records follow.
Biographical Note
Joan Marie Banks was born in London, England, the daughter of Sir Maurice and Anne Banks. Her mother was an American and when, as a young teenager, Dunlop visited the US, she then decided she wanted to live here. She applied and was accepted at Vassar College but her parents insisted that she attend a London secretarial school instead. After graduation, she worked for the BBC before emigrating to America in 1960. After a brief stint at a Manhattan advertising agency, Dunlop went to work at the Ford Foundation (1960-1967) as an administrative assistant to the Director of Public Affairs, Paul Ylvisaker, at a time when the Public Affairs Programs would soon serve as the model for President Lyndon Johnson's Great Society/War on Poverty programs. In the late-1960s, she worked for the City of New York in the Mayor's Office of the Budget and at the Fund for the City of New York. During the 1970s, Dunlop worked as senior advisor to John D. Rockefeller, III, and provided administrative support to his organization, the Population Council where she worked to broaden the agency's research into gender roles and sexuality. According to her obituary in the New York Times (2012-07-01),"she introduced Mr. Rockefeller to feminist leaders, including Germaine Greer and Gloria Steinem." In 1984, Dunlop became president of the organization which would become her life's work when she joined the International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC). For the next fourteen years, she oversaw the tremendous growth of the IWHC as she secured its"reputation as an authoritative voice for women's perspectives in population policy. When she left in 1998, Dunlop continued her work for women and reproductive rights around the world through an independent project, A Women's Lens on Global Issues. She carried on with her consulting work even after she began her third, and final, bout with breast cancer in 2006. Married and divorced twice, Joan Dunlop, according to the New York Times, "devoted herself to expanding women's rights to control their own bodies"(2012-07-01) and did so on a global scale.
Related Materials
Population and Reproductive Health Oral History Project and Adrienne Germain papers
Scope and Contents
The collection contains Joan Banks Dunlop's personal and professional papers, including correspondence, reports, daybooks and monthly calendars, legal documents, diaries, and photographs (most unidentified). Especially well documented is Dunlop's work with the International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC) and A Women's Lens on Global Issues.
Appraisal
In 2019, approximately 5 record boxes of materials were removed from the collection. Of these, 4 record boxes contained Dunlop's personal financial and medical information, which was destroyed per the donor agreement. 1 record carton of materials was also destroyed that related to the Flora Murphy case (2002-2003) in which a woman going through a nasty divorce was charged with child abuse for not intervening when her teenage son sexually assaulted his younger sister. Staff decided to destroy this material, since many records contained records of a sexual assault on a minor, icluding the police report. The Flora Murphy material was in the collection because Dunlop and two other women came to the aid of Murphy, emotionally, legally and financially, and Dunlop created the Flora Murphy Fund to support Murphy through the trial. A small amount of duplicates were also removed from the collection and discarded.
Birth control -- Developing countries -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Birth control -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Women's health services -- International; International Women's Health Coalition; Rockefeller, John D., 1906-1978; Address books; Agendas; Annual reports; Appointment books; articles; Business cards; clippings; correspondence; Court cases; Calendars; Electronic mail; Financial records; Galley proofs; Greeting cards; Invoices; Legal files; Medical records; Negatives; notebooks; Notes; Oral histories; photographs; Proceedings; Programs; Proposals; reports; Research; Resumes; Speeches; Dunlop, Joan Banks; Dunlop, Joan Banks
- Rockefeller Foundation- Abortion, 1972-1985 (Box 1)
- Rockefeller Foundation- Candidates for Population Council, 1975 (Box 1)
- Rockefeller Foundation- Career Development, 1980 (Box 1)
- Rockefeller Foundation- Correspondence, 1973-1979 (Box 1)
- Rockefeller Foundation- Issues and Opportunities, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
- Rockefeller Foundation- Project on Human Sexual Development, 1973-1977 (Box 1)
- Rockefeller Foundation- "Whither Women and Development" Report, 1981 (Box 1)
- Rockefeller Foundation- Writings and Interesting Articles, 1964-1975 (Box 1)
- Ford Foundation, 1980-2002 (Box 1)
- New York Public Library, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
- New York Public Library - Joan Dunlop acceptance, 1981 (Box 9)
- International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC)- Appointment, 1984 (Box 1)
- International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC)- General, 1984-1998 (Box 1, Box 2)
- International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC)- General, 2008-2011 (Box 2)
- International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC)- Evaluation - Jennifer Dowley, 2005 (Box 9)
- International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC)- Evaluation - Germain, 1985 (Box 9)
- International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC)- Transition- Germain, 2010-2011 (Box 11, Box 12)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Materials related to Adrienne Germain leaving the IWHC and Françoise Girard's appointment are closed until 2033.
  Scope and Contents
  These materials are related to Adrienne Germain's leaving IWHC, including correspondence, meeting minutes, and legal documents.
- International Women's Health Coalition (IWHC)- Transition- Girard, 2011-2012 (Box 11)
  These materials are related to Françoise Girard's appointment to the President of the IWHC, including correspondence, meeting minutes, and interview notes.
- Open Society Institute - Executive Director search, 2012 (Box 9)
- Foundation for Community Health - Evaluation - Georgina Lucas (from Smith College SSW), 2003 (Box 9)
- Foundation for Community Health - CEO evaluations and personnel issues, 2006-2009 (Box 9)
- Research - "The Exchange Report: Women in the Third World", 1989 (Box 13)
- Correspondence- Joan and Arthur, 2008 (Box 6)
- Correspondence- Yannick Banks, 2009-2012 (Box 6)
- Correspondence- Rob's Wedding, 2004 (Box 6)
- Correspondence- From Ruth Hall Banks to Sister Mabel, 1939-1940 (Box 6)
- Personal- Ed Deagle and Hughes Aircraft, 1987-1989 (Box 6)
- Photos, 1982-1999 (Box 6)
- Photos- Joan Dunlop (Box 6)
- Photos- Joan Dunlop by Penelope West (Box 6)
- Photos- Ed Deagle (Box 6)
- Photos- Joan Dunlop and Rachel Kyte Office Farewell Party (Box 6)
- Photos- Joan Dunlop and Carrot (Cat) (Box 6)
- Calendars, 1979-2012 (Box 8, Box 9)
- Calendars, 1987-2010 (Box 13)
- Memoir - "Making Sense of It All", 2007-2011 (Box 9)
- Oral History - Smith College, 2003-2012 (Box 9)
- Poetry, no date (Box 9)
- Divorce, 1972-1992 (Box 12)
  Materials related to Joan Dunlop's divorces restricted until 2028.
  This material largely includes correspondence related to Joan Dunlop's divorces from Ed Deagle and Peter Dunlop.
- Diploma - Hamilton College, 1995 (Box 13)